So this is the moment you have been waiting for.
It's time to create our first project.
To make a new project, all you need to do is click the big create button at the top of the page, and
this creates a brand new project for you and takes you to the Scratch Project editor, where all the
awesome stuff happens.
Now that we're in the place where all the action happens, let's take a tour so you can get a quick
understanding of how it all works.
So this whole area that we're in at the moment is called The editor.
And this is where you can design and code your project.
It's basically where you will create anything you can imagine.
The scratch editor has four main parts the stage, the sprites, the code blocks, and the scripts.
Let me explain what each part does.
All right, let's first talk about the stage area.
You'll find it on the far right of your screen.
The stage is where all the fun stuff happens.
Just like a stage in a theater.
This is where you see the action as you create your project.
Everything you make will appear right here.
It's the special space where you can see and build your amazing project.
Now, looking down from the stage, you will see this area here where you can choose the background
of the stage.
Currently we just have this boring plain background selected, but if you click on this little button
on the bottom right, you can choose a new backdrop, plus add sounds and music to the stage.
But we'll explore all that in a future lesson.
A scratch sprite is the character that your scratch code controls.
For example, you may write some code to make your sprite move around or talk.
These sprites can be all sorts of things, ranging from people to animals to objects.
And just like with backdrops for the stage, you can choose from loads of pre-made sprites or even draw
your very own unique wines.
Plus, you can even upload sprites from your computer, which we'll be doing in future lessons.
Next are the code blocks.
These are the instructions that you can use to make your sprites do things.
It's just like real world programming, but instead of typing out complex lines of text, you use these
blocks.
But essentially you're doing the same thing you're coding.
There are different categories of blocks such as motion looks, sound events, control, and many more.
Each category represents a different aspect of programming, helping you to build a complete and interactive
project.
To use these code blocks, simply drag and drop them from the block palette into the script area, and
as you put the blocks together, you will start to see your project come to life.
And speaking of the scripts area, this is the last major area we must discuss.
This is where we put blocks together in a special order that tells your sprites what to do.
You can connect code blocks together by snapping them like puzzle pieces.
Just as a quick example, I will bring this move ten steps block onto my window here.
As you can see, if I click it, my cat sprite moves forward on the screen.
And lastly, if you look to the very top, you will see that there are these different tabs for costumes
and sounds.
Now these are also very important spaces that will help us create stunning projects, but we will get
into that later on.
But for now, that's a quick overview of the scratch interface and how it all works and carries you
to play around and check out things for yourself, because that's where the learning happens in the
doing.
I look forward to seeing you in the next lesson, where we will start to see what all this code does.